<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A lamentation over Cambridge, and also a visitation to the inhabitants thereof who have not yet sinned out the day of their mercy, and worn out the patience of the Lord.</title>
            <author>Aynsloe, John, d. 1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26273</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A4295</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20354</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12259122</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12259122</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57751</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26273)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57751)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 9:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A lamentation over Cambridge, and also a visitation to the inhabitants thereof who have not yet sinned out the day of their mercy, and worn out the patience of the Lord.</title>
                  <author>Aynsloe, John, d. 1693.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[Jan.] 1664 [i.e. 1665]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"An epistle written in the movings of Gods Holy Spirit" signed: John Aynsloe.</note>
                  <note>On publication: Printed in the first moneth.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Includes: "An epistle written in the movings of Gods Holy Spirit unto the elect people of God everywhere" and "For the flock in God in the town of Colchester."</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:57751:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A LAMENTATION over CAMBRIDGE, AND ALSO A Viſitation to the Inhabitants thereof; Who have not yet ſinned out the day of their Mercy, and worn out the Patience of the Lord.</head>
            <p>OH! thou Town of <hi>Cambridge!</hi> what ſort of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation and mourning ſhall I take up for thee? how ſhall I lament thy ſad Eſtate and condition, my tongue is not able to utter the grief of my heart, for thy Inhabitants who have ſo long grieved the Lords Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and reſiſted his Appearance in thee by his Light and Spirit, which is given to heal thee, and all people: But Oh, you Inhabitants of <hi>Cambridge</hi> how have you ſlighted it, and rebelled againſt the Lord dayes without number, and have ſtill continued in your wickedneſs, and idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous practices, and have highly provoked the Lord in acting that which you ſaw to be evil, which his righteous witneſs in your Conſciences did reprove you off, and which many of you were and are convinced of in your Conſciences to be evil; yet notwithſtanding, you have done that evil which you were convinced of, which is a grievous provogation of the Lord; and the ground of it is becauſe you were not faithful unto the Lord in what he convinced you of, but for fear of man, and alſo the reproach that might fall upon you, if you departed from iniquity, yee have rather choſen to obey <hi>Man</hi> then the Lord, that yee might ſave your ſelves from that which <hi>Man</hi> could do unto you; but <hi>alaſs, alaſs, who ſhall ſave you from the ſtroak of the Lords hand,</hi> which is now ready to fall upon you, who now will ſtand in the <hi>Gapp;</hi> will your <hi>Teachers</hi> whom you have followed, will they ſave you, or are they able to ſave themſelves? who is ſo wiſe among them as to diſcern the cauſe? which of them can find out the ground of the matter? hath not fearfulneſs ſurprized the hearts of all? who can ſay, his heart is clean, and he hath no hand in procuring this which is come, and may yet further come; do you not now ſee? <hi>In vain is the help of Man;</hi> have yee not been often told it by the deſpiſed people of God called <hi>Quakers,</hi> that <hi>in vain was the help of Man, whoſe Breath is in his noſtrils;</hi> and hath not the Lord raiſed up this people, and ſent early and late among you, exhorting you to ceaſe from following of <hi>Man,</hi> and to turn to the Lord, and be obedient to his <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> manifeſted in you: And have not they born a faithful Teſtimony among you, in your <hi>Markets,</hi> in your <hi>Streets,</hi> in your <hi>Colledges,</hi> &amp;c. and have they not been evilly intreated by you? <hi>Oh yee Inhabitants</hi> of <hi>Cambridge!</hi> and was not the firſt <hi>PERSEC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TION</hi> begun among you in all theſe Parts, and was it not in this <hi>Street,</hi> where the Lord hath begun to ſtretch forth his hand; and hath not even all the <hi>Perſecution</hi> that hath been ever ſince begun in that <hi>Street:</hi> Oh conſider and lay to heart, ye Inhabitants of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and repent and turn unto the Lord, and love his Appearance in you, for yet a little while is given you to return; take heed of ſligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of it: And thus I was moved of the Lord to write theſe few lines unto you, for the Seeds ſake which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you; and that the honeſt hearted may know for what the Lord is offended with you, and be ſeparated in their hearts and converſations, leaſt they alſo feel the ſtroak of the Lords hand, for the Lord is certainly riſen to plead the Cauſe of his innocent and oppreſſed People, for he hath heard their <hi>Cryes</hi> and their <hi>Groanes,</hi> even as ſure as he heard <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the dayes paſt, and will as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly deliver them from all their <hi>Oppreſſions;</hi> and well will it be for them that have had no hand nor conſent in <hi>Perſecuting</hi> of them; for the Lord will certainly take their parts more eminently then he hath yet done, even to the <hi>Aſtoniſhment</hi> of their Enemies, and to the opening of the eyes of many that they may ſee and diſcern the cauſe of the Lords <hi>Controverſie with England:</hi> But oh, thou Town of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> there is yet ſomething in my heart to write unto thee, and that is, that every one may ſearch their own hearts, with the Light of Chriſt, Gods righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and true witneſs which he hath placed in your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences; and every one depart from that which it lets you ſee to be evil, and let it ſearch your hearts, and be ſubject unto it; for that is it that muſt ſtand in the <hi>Gapp,</hi> and cauſe the judgment to be removed, for it is your tranſgreſſion againſt the Lords witneſs, and appearance in you, which is the cauſe of his judgments breaking forth amongſt you. (and in this Nation) And thus I have cleared my Conſcience in the ſight of God, (concerning you) and whether you hear or forbear I am clear of your blood, who am ſubject to the motion of Gods Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; and this is the meſſage of the Lord unto you through his Servant.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. A.</signed>
               <dateline>Written on <date>the firſt day of the week being the 6. day of the 6. Month 1665.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:57751:2"/>
            <head>An Epiſtle written in the movings of Gods holy Spirit unto the Elect People of God every where.</head>
            <p>DEar Friends, Brethren &amp; Siſters of the birth of the morning of the day which is ſprung from on high, which hath vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited us; unto you all is the breathing of my Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hers love through my veſſell; &amp; in the tenderneſſe of my heart, &amp; moving of the ſpirit of life do I dearly ſalute every one of you, having you all freſh in my mind before the Lord, wiſhing well unto you all, as my own ſoul, and deſiring of the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d that ye may never want the enjoyment of his life and love, which at this time I am filled withall towards you, and which I feel is ſtill in ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e for you and all that are not yet brought home, my ſoul travelleth for them and you, that all may be brought into the reſt, and alſo continue in it, for great ſhakings of heart may ſtill be to come, to try every birth, that that which is born of God may only ſtand and be approved in his ſight, and all falſe births will fail and fall before the Lord, and will not ſtand in the day of try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, though it may make a great ſhew for a time, and boaſt it ſelf in its many ſufferings, and conqueſts, and glory over others, with its many words and great ſhew, yet it will come ſhort of the bleſſing, and the inheritance of God is not for it: therefore dear friends, I warn you all in Gods fear and holy awe, that ye watch diligently over your own hearts, that ſuch a birth be not found amongſt you, for that is it will betray the juſt for ſomething of this world, therefore beware of it, for it ſeeks it ſelf and its own honour, and not the good of all, nor Gods glory; by this ye ſhall know it, it breathes downwards, and will ſay, ſave thy ſelf; but the pure holy gentle Seed and birth of the holy God, its cry is unto him, and its eye is towards him, and it ſayes, ſhall I not drink the cup which my heavenly Father giveth me? and ſhall I not follow the Lamb through the great tribulation, and lie down in the will of the heavenly Father, and be content in all conditions, and it murmures not at any tryal, but chearfully and joyfully paſſes through all, rejoicing that it is found worthy to bear his teſtimony, and that it hath a croſſe to bear, though it meet with a Crown of thorns, from the world, and ſpittings and mockings from the men thereof; yet the preſent enjoyment of its God, in the midſt of them makes up all, and conſtrains it to ſay (in the ſtrength of his love) all theſe things is but little; in compariſon of what thou art to me, how can I anſwer thy love, oh my God! ſo it wearies not in its journey, nor faints not by the way, becauſe the Lord is its portion, and the place of of its reſt; oh dear friends feel this birth in your hearts which breathes upwards, and ſeeks thoſe things which are above, and is not intangled with the things of this world, with the cares of it, and fears of it, but caſts its cares upon God, and believes beyond all, and its faith removes the mountains, and it hath the evidence thereof in its ſelf, and is of <hi>Abraham,</hi> For it ſtaggers not concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the promiſe, though <hi>Sarahs</hi> womb be dry, this is the birth that my life travelleth for, and that which my God will ſtand by, and deliver out of all its afflictions, and will raiſe it up in the brightneſſe of his ariſings and glory of his appearance, and bleſſed and happy are they that hath part in this firſt reſurrection, for over them the ſecond death ſhall have no power, and they ſhall be reckoned in the number of Gods elect, which cannot be deceived, &amp; they are builded on that rock which the gates of hell cannot prevail againſt, but all others ſhall beſhatter'd &amp; ſcatter'd, the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it, &amp; it muſt ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come to paſſe, therefore be awakened, oh every one of ye who profeſſe the name of the Lord, and put on your beautiful garments (which is the covering of Gods holy pure ſpirit) and meet the Bridegroom; prepare, prepare to meet him, for in power and great glory is he come, and coming, and every eye ſhall ſee him, but the ſlumbering ſpirit ſhall be ſhut out; but the bride that is prepared for her husband ſhall enter; for now is the Kingdome of Heaven like unto ten Virgins, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is in my heart, from the mighty God, to warn all to watch and be diligent, that none loſe their Crown, and miſſe of their reſt after ſo long a travell; for ſurely my cry is, Lord ſave thy people, that none of them periſh in the wilderneſſe, but that <hi>Ioſuah</hi>'s ſpirit may be found amongſt them, that all may paſſe the River <hi>Iordan;</hi> even <hi>So be it,</hi> Amen, ſaith your Brother in the tribulation, kingdome, and Patience of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Cambridge <hi>County Gaol,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 13. <hi>of the firſt Moneth,</hi> 1664.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>JOHN AYNSLOE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>For the FLOCK of God in the Town of <hi>Colcheſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>DEar Friends and ſuffering Lambs, whom I dearly love and tenderly imbrace in the arms of my Fathers love, which flows in me towards you and all my ſuffering Friends and Brethren every where, and alſo to the whole flock of my Fathers fold, the breathing of my life is for you, and the ſalutation of my love is unto you in the Town of <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> who is called to bear you teſtimony in this day for the living God, and is found faithful in your tryal, and ſhrinks not at the ſharpneſſe thereof, though it hath exceeded others. Surely it is becauſe the Lord is with you, and ſtands by you, and ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles you to bear and ſuffer what he ſuffereth to be done unto you for the tryal of your faith and patience, that ye may be approved of in his ſight, and manifeſted unto all your enemies that ye are of God. Oh ye Valiants in Iſrael, my heart loves you, and my life is refreſhed in you: go on and proſper, and let it never repent you of what you have ſuffered or may ſuffer for his Names ſake, for ſurely your reward is from God, and no man can take your crown from you; and happy are ye whom God hath counted worthy to bear ſuch a teſtimony which is ſo much renowned in the hearts of your Brethren, and ſo much in remembrance before the Lord; and ſtrong are the cries that are put up for you, that ye ſaint not, which ſurely prevail with God on your behalf, for how can you ſuffer and we not partake with you, and bear part of your burthen, and contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute our aſſiſtance for your help by ſupplicating to God for you, as the life doth ariſe in our hearts, which is all that we can do, having our own help from him, And now my dear friends and fellow-ſufferers in the kingdom, and patience of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, what have we to glory in in all this? wherein can we rejoyce ſave that our names are written in the book of life? what hath the Lord done for us? how can we anſwer his love? what can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſo dear to us as our God? what is ſo precious as his life? what can we not part withall rather then it? what can we not ſuffer in body and eſtate, rather then to be deprived of the light of his countenance? is not this the cry of our hearts, Lord lift thou up thy countenance upon us, and then we have enough, and be thou the portion of our cup, and which of us can ſay but he hath dealt bountifully with us, and doth ſpread our table, and cauſe our cup to overflow in the ſight of our enemies, and many are the experiences we have had of his love, day by day he hath not ceaſed to do us good; how hath he engaged our hearts unto himſelf? O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the remembrance of his love is freſh upon my heart, and I cannot but communicate it unto you, that we may rejoyce together and praiſe the name of the Lord. And friends, be ye ſtill valiant for the truth upon the earth, keep your ground, and ye ſhall gain more. Weary not in well doing, for ſurely you ſhall have your reward, if you faint no: fight the good fight of faith, look over all the hardſhip unto the Lord, and he will ſweeten your cup, and make your trial eaſie. But wo to the enemies of Sion, better they had never been born, then thus to vex and trouble Iſrael, who would only paſſe through their countrey, and eat our own bre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d and drink our own water, and not fowl their ſprings, but the heathen rage, and the people are angry, becauſe of what the Lord is about to do in the earth. But be ye ſtill in your tents, and quiet in your habitations which ye have in God: theſe things will paſſe over, and the remembrance will be no more ſo. Think not the time long, nor your trial hard, but ly down in the heavenly will of the heavenly God, that his will may be done on earth as it is in heaven, which is the travel of your ſuffering Brother.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Cambridge Caſtle</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 7. <hi>of </hi> the 1. <hi>Moneth,</hi> 1664.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>J. A.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed in the firſt Moneth, 1664.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
